<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="llg.con.054.01">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Foreign Relations for 1907, Investigation of Affairs in the Kongo</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
 
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Locating Lord Greystoke</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">llg.con.054.01</idno>
</publicationStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="United States Department of State">United States Department of State</author>
<title level="a" type="main">Investigation of Affairs in the Kongo</title>
<title level="m">Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
<date when="1906">1907</date>
<pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
<publisher>U.S. Government Printing Office</publisher>
<biblScope type="pages">791-829</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
 
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage> 
 
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="labels">
<term/>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="getty" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="llg.con.054.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>
 
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
   
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-11-19" who="#kln">initial transcription and encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
 
</teiHeader>

<text>

<group>

<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d001">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">The Consul-General at Boma to the Secretary of State</head>

<head type="sub">[Extract.]</head>

<head type="sub">American Consulate-General, Boma, December 1, 1906.</head>

<p>Sir: I have the honor to transmit herewith a confidential report concerning the Kongo Free State as a commercial undertaking.</p>

<p>I beg to inform the department that this report is based upon personal observation, personal reading of public documents, and conversations with officials, traders, and other trustworthy men of affiars.</p>

<p>I have, etc.,<lb/>
Clarence Rice Slocum.</p>

<div2 type="enclosure">

<head type="main">[Inclosure.]</head>

<head type="main">The Kongo Free State as a Commercial Undertaking.</head>

<head type="sub">Boma, December 1, 1906.</head>

<p>I have the honor to report that I find the Kongo Free State, under the present régime, to be nothing but a vast commercial enterprise for the exploitation of the products of the country, particularly that of ivory and rubber.</p>

<p>Admitted by Belgian officials and other foreigners here, the State, as I find it, is not open to trade in the intended sense of article 5 of the Berlin act, under which the State was formed.</p>

<p>The State's regulations as to taxation of river craft is such as to preclude the possibility of private competition in the waters of the Kongo and its affluents, and thus, in my opinion, creates a violation of the spirit of the same act.</p>

<p>The governing power of the State has apparently made every effort to discourage trade in its proper sense, constantly increasing taxation and various restrictions which, I shall point out further on, have all tended to discourage the traders of years' standing here, especially as no public improvements have been made worthy of comment.</p>

<p>While it is true that Boma, the capital, presents a much different appearance than was the case a few years ago, and that railroads have been constructed in the lower and upper Kongo, I state that this has been done for the benefit of the State, or rather, to be exact, the controller of the Kongo Free State, and as an aid to the exploitation(?) of the products of the country; while, on the contrary, public utilities, such as sewers, water pipes, etc., have not been constructed except a few kilometers here at Boma, where the tax for obtaining the service is so exorbitant that few are willing to pay it.</p>

<p>With all the vast exportation of rubber and ivory, and its compensating value in European markets, not even a closed shed as a receptacle of imported goods exists in Boma.</p>

<p>The quays at Boma and Matadi belong to railroad companies, in one of which the State is reputed to possess no interest.</p>

<p>The charges are deemed so excessive that the boats of the Compagnie Belge Maritime du Congo are the only ones to employ this means of discharging their cargo.</p>

<p>The German, French, Portuguese, and English boats discharge their cargo into small boats, which are beached, and occasionally the contents spoiled through this necessity of trade.</p>

<p>At Matadi, I believe, the French boats pay the rate demanded and dock accordingly.</p>

<p>Rubber.</p>

<p>It is practically impossible for the trader to purchase and vend at a profit this commodity, as, in accordance with a decree of the King Sovereign under date of September 22, 1904, every trader purchasing rubber must, for every 100 kilograms or fraction collected from trees or vines, plant 50 trees, and for herb rubber collected or purchased in like quantity, 15 trees.</p>

<p>If the trader possesses no ground upon which to plant the trees required, and it is obvious that he has none, as none can purchase land in quantity sufficient for such purposes, he must plant on the territory of the State and the trees become the property of the State thereby, and this notwithstanding the fact that the trader pays import and export duties, in addition to other taxes, such as that for the recruiting of clerks, office boys, servants, etc. -- thus, 100 francs for a license to recruit the same, and an additional tax of 300 francs per head for every clerical employee (black or white), including the manager.</p>

<p>As a proof of the utter absurdity of the law governing the planting of trees, I beg to offer the following incident:</p>

<p>A certain trader of Thysville, having bought rubber, was informed that he would have to conform to the law as stated above.</p>

<p>He asked that ground might be indicated to him where he could plant the required trees, but was officially informed, wherein lies the pith of my remarks on this subject, that he could plant at Leopoldville, a distance of 160 kilometers interior.</p>

<p>However, the more serious obstacle to rubber trading, so far as the "free trade" is concerned, is the export tax on this product, namely, the conventional tax for the present year of 40 centimes per kilogram, a supplementary tax of 25 centimes, and a further domanial tax of 25 centimes -- thus, 90 centimes per kilogram -- which, it is to be noted, si a higher rate than the State allows the native for rubber furnished in payment of taxes, which varies, for no apparent reason, from 35 to 50 centimes per kilogram.</p>

<p>Ivory.</p>

<p>The commercialism of the State or its governing power is further evidenced in the local (?) ordinance of September 30, 1905, regarding the stamping of ivory; thus, for each elephant killed, one tusk becomes the property of the State (?) and the other must now, by the ordinance referred to, be stamped before being placed on the market.</p>

<p>As the chiefs of the posts charged with this duty are also charged with the purchase of </p>

</div2>


</div1>

</body>

</text>




</group>

</text>

</TEI>
