<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="llg.con.054.01">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Foreign Relations for 1907, Investigation of Affairs in the Kongo</title>
<principal n="Jones, Jeannette Eileen, 1970-">Jeannette Eileen Jones</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name n="Nash, Kaci L." xml:id="kln">Kaci L. Nash</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
 
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2014</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
 
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Locating Lord Greystoke</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<idno type="project">llg.con.054.01</idno>
</publicationStmt>
 
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="United States Department of State">United States Department of State</author>
<title level="a" type="main">Investigation of Affairs in the Kongo</title>
<title level="m">Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations of the United States</title>
<date when="1906">1907</date>
<pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
<publisher>U.S. Government Printing Office</publisher>
<biblScope type="pages">791-829</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
 
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage> 
 
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="theme">
<term>Congo Free State</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="type">
<term>Document</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="original" n="subtype">
<term>Report</term>
</keywords>

<keywords scheme="viaf" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="labels">
<term/>
</keywords> 
 
<keywords scheme="getty" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<keywords scheme="original" n="ethnic_group">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="language">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="religion">
<term/>
</keywords>
 
<classCode scheme="original">
<ref type="analysis" target="llg.con.054.02">Analysis</ref>
</classCode>
 
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
   
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2014-11-19" who="#kln">initial transcription and encoding</change>
</revisionDesc>
 
</teiHeader>

<text>

<group>

<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d001">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">The Consul-General at Boma to the Secretary of State</head>

<head type="sub">[Extract.]</head>

<head type="sub">American Consulate-General, Boma, December 1, 1906.</head>

<p>Sir: I have the honor to transmit herewith a confidential report concerning the Kongo Free State as a commercial undertaking.</p>

<p>I beg to inform the department that this report is based upon personal observation, personal reading of public documents, and conversations with officials, traders, and other trustworthy men of affiars.</p>

<p>I have, etc.,<lb/>
Clarence Rice Slocum.</p>

<div2 type="enclosure">

<head type="main">[Inclosure.]</head>

<head type="main">The Kongo Free State as a Commercial Undertaking.</head>

<head type="sub">Boma, December 1, 1906.</head>

<p>I have the honor to report that I find the Kongo Free State, under the present régime, to be nothing but a vast commercial enterprise for the exploitation of the products of the country, particularly that of ivory and rubber.</p>

<p>Admitted by Belgian officials and other foreigners here, the State, as I find it, is not open to trade in the intended sense of article 5 of the Berlin act, under which the State was formed.</p>

<p>The State's regulations as to taxation of river craft is such as to preclude the possibility of private competition in the waters of the Kongo and its affluents, and thus, in my opinion, creates a violation of the spirit of the same act.</p>

<p>The governing power of the State has apparently made every effort to discourage trade in its proper sense, constantly increasing taxation and various restrictions which, I shall point out further on, have all tended to discourage the traders of years' standing here, especially as no public improvements have been made worthy of comment.</p>

<p>While it is true that Boma, the capital, presents a much different appearance than was the case a few years ago, and that railroads have been constructed in the lower and upper Kongo, I state that this has been done for the benefit of the State, or rather, to be exact, the controller of the Kongo Free State, and as an aid to the exploitation(?) of the products of the country; while, on the contrary, public utilities, such as sewers, water pipes, etc., have not been constructed except a few kilometers here at Boma, where the tax for obtaining the service is so exorbitant that few are willing to pay it.</p>

<p>With all the vast exportation of rubber and ivory, and its compensating value in European markets, not even a closed shed as a receptacle of imported goods exists in Boma.</p>

<p>The quays at Boma and Matadi belong to railroad companies, in one of which the State is reputed to possess no interest.</p>

<p>The charges are deemed so excessive that the boats of the Compagnie Belge Maritime du Congo are the only ones to employ this means of discharging their cargo.</p>

<p>The German, French, Portuguese, and English boats discharge their cargo into small boats, which are beached, and occasionally the contents spoiled through this necessity of trade.</p>

<p>At Matadi, I believe, the French boats pay the rate demanded and dock accordingly.</p>

<p>Rubber.</p>

<p>It is practically impossible for the trader to purchase and vend at a profit this commodity, as, in accordance with a decree of the King Sovereign under date of September 22, 1904, every trader purchasing rubber must, for every 100 kilograms or fraction collected from trees or vines, plant 50 trees, and for herb rubber collected or purchased in like quantity, 15 trees.</p>

<p>If the trader possesses no ground upon which to plant the trees required, and it is obvious that he has none, as none can purchase land in quantity sufficient for such purposes, he must plant on the territory of the State and the trees become the property of the State thereby, and this notwithstanding the fact that the trader pays import and export duties, in addition to other taxes, such as that for the recruiting of clerks, office boys, servants, etc. -- thus, 100 francs for a license to recruit the same, and an additional tax of 300 francs per head for every clerical employee (black or white), including the manager.</p>

<p>As a proof of the utter absurdity of the law governing the planting of trees, I beg to offer the following incident:</p>

<p>A certain trader of Thysville, having bought rubber, was informed that he would have to conform to the law as stated above.</p>

<p>He asked that ground might be indicated to him where he could plant the required trees, but was officially informed, wherein lies the pith of my remarks on this subject, that he could plant at Leopoldville, a distance of 160 kilometers interior.</p>

<p>However, the more serious obstacle to rubber trading, so far as the "free trade" is concerned, is the export tax on this product, namely, the conventional tax for the present year of 40 centimes per kilogram, a supplementary tax of 25 centimes, and a further domanial tax of 25 centimes -- thus, 90 centimes per kilogram -- which, it is to be noted, si a higher rate than the State allows the native for rubber furnished in payment of taxes, which varies, for no apparent reason, from 35 to 50 centimes per kilogram.</p>

<p>Ivory.</p>

<p>The commercialism of the State or its governing power is further evidenced in the local (?) ordinance of September 30, 1905, regarding the stamping of ivory; thus, for each elephant killed, one tusk becomes the property of the State (?) and the other must now, by the ordinance referred to, be stamped before being placed on the market.</p>

<p>As the chiefs of the posts charged with this duty are also charged with the purchase of ivory for the State, it is natural to presume that very little of the ivory reaches the open market, and, in fact, does not.</p>

<p>Résumé</p>

<p>There being no money in circulation in the interior of the State, the taxes are paid in kind, for the most part in rubber.</p>

<p>The same is equally true of the colonial territory of the French Republic in the Kongo; but where the French Government have periodical sales of the products collected for taxes, enabling thereby the ordinary trader to acquire at its market value that produce and ship to Europe, the Free State, on the contrary, ships all produce so collected for its own account.</p>

<p>It is obvious that this report applies principally to the domanial lands and not to the produce of the concessionary companies.</p>

<p>As to the concessionary companies, it is obvious that where there is no competition the native is at the mercy of  the concessionaire, so far as the value of the goods given in exchange is concerned.</p>

<p>In my opinion, it is thus obvious that under the system prevailing at the present time in the Kongo Free State, the just equivalent of foreign manufactures can not enter, and thus what should be a profitable market for the foreign producer, if the spirit of the Berlin act were carried out, is lost.</p>

<p>That this is true is born out by the fact that there are no private traders in the upper Kongo with the exception of five trading companies at Stanleyville, which enjoy somewhat of a privilege in trading in what is known as the Free Zone, an area of about 50 by 10 kilometers.</p>

<p>It is common report here, even among the officials of Belgian origin, that in every one of the concessionary companies the State holds the controlling interest.</p>

<p>I have no means at my disposal to prove this statement.</p>

<p>Respectfully submitted.<lb/>
Clarence Rice Slocum, Consul-General.</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>




<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d002">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">The Secretary of State to Chargé Carter</head>

<head type="sub">[Telegram.]</head>

<head type="sub">Department of State, Washington, December 10, 1906.</head>

<p>Moved by the deep interest shown by all classes of the American people in the amelioration of conditions in the Kongo State, the President has observed with keen appreciation the steps which the British Government is considering toward that humanitarian end. You will say so to Sir Edward Grey, inviting from him such information as to the course and scope of the action which Great Britain may contemplate under the provisions of the general act of the Kongo and in view of the information which the British Government may have acquired concerning the conditions in Central Africa, and you will further express to Sir Edward Grey the desire of the President to contribute by such action and attitude as may be properly within his power toward the realization of whatever reforms may be counseled by the sentiments of humanity and by the experience developed by the past and present workings of Kongo administration. The President's interest in watching the trend toward reform is coupled with the earnest desire to see the full performance of the obligations of articles 2 and 5 of the general Africa slave-trade act of Brussels of July 2, 1890, to which the United States is a party, in all that  affects involuntary servitude of the natives.</p>

<p>Root.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>





<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d003">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">Chargé Carter to the Secretary of State.</head>

<head type="sub">[Telegram.]</head>

<head type="sub">American Embassy, London, December 12, 1906.</head>

<p>With reference to your telegraphic instruction of 10th instant, received yesterday, I saw Sir Edward Grey same afternoon. He was much gratified to learn of the President's interest and the attitude of our Government in regard to the amelioration of conditions in the Kongo. His Majesty's Government are not at present advised of the attitude of the other signatory powers in this regard, but they think, in view of the reports of their own agents and that of the Belgian King's commission, that a radical change is necessary in the management of affairs in the Kongo. He specified more especially the conditions of forced labor in rubber under guise of taxation, which was practical slavery, leaving out of consideration the various reports of cruelty and other atrocities. He felt that there should be a parliament behind the government in the Kongo, by which he meant that the Belgian Government should become responsible for the administration of affairs in that locality. he therefore had postponed any action to await the result of the present debate upon the subject now going on in the Belgian Parliament. He seemed to think the main obstacle in the way to annexation by Belgium was the difficulty in agreeing upon terms with the King. In the event, however, of the Belgian Government not being able to arrive at such a conclusion His Majesty's Government would feel constrained to address a note to the signatory powers, suggesting a conference. He nevertheless hoped that such a contingency might be avoided by the action of Belgium, and he promised to keep us promptly informed of any developments.</p>

<p>Carter.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>





<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d004">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">Chargé Carter to the Secretary of State.</head>

<head type="sub">American Embassy, London, December 14, 1906.</head>

<p>Sir: I have the honor to inclose herewith a translation of your telegram, dated the 10th instant and received at this embassy on the morning of the 11th, respecting affairs in the Kongo, and also a translation of my telegram in reply thereto of the 12th instant.</p>

<p>In this connection I have the honor to inclose herewith a clipping from the Times of this date reporting a reply made by Sir Edward Grey in the House of Commons to a question put by Mr. Alden, the member for Middlesex, as to whether there would be an international conference to consider the situation in the Kongo Free State. It will be perceived that the answer mentioned was doubtless based upon the information which I conveyed to him at your instance.</p>

<p>I have, etc.,<lb/>
John Ridgely Carter.</p>

<div2 type="enclosure">

<head type="main">[Inclosure 1.]</head>

<head type="main">Memorandum</head>

<head type="sub">Handed by the American chargé d'affaires ad interim to the British secretary of state for foreign affairs December 11, 1906</head>

<p>The President, moved by deep interest shown by all classes of the American people in the amelioration of conditions in the Kongo State, has observed with keen appreciation the steps which His Majesty's Government are considering toward that humanitarian end. The American Government would be glad to have such information as to the course and scope of action as Great Britain may contemplate under the provisions of the general act of the Kongo, having in view the information which His Majesty's Government may have acquired concerning the conditions in Central Africa, it being the desire of the President to contribute by such action and attitude as may be properly within his function toward the realization of whatever reforms may be counseled by the sentiments of humanity and by the experience developed by the past and present workings of the administration of the Kongo.</p>

<p>The President's interest in watching the trend toward reform is coupled with the earnest desire to see the full performance of the obligations of articles 2 and 5 of the general Africa slave-trade act of Brussels of July 2, 1890, to which the United States is a party, in all that affects involuntary servitude of the natives.</p>

<p>December 11, 1906.</p>

</div2>

<div2 type="enclosure">

<head type="main">[Inclosure 2.]</head>

<head type="main">[The Times, Friday, December 14, 1906.]</head>

<head type="sub">The Kongo.</head>

<p>Sir E. Grey, replying to a question of Mr. Alden (Middlesex, Tottenham) as to an international conference to consider the situation in the Kongo Free State, said:</p>

<p>"The plan of summoning an international conference has not specifically been mentioned. But the United States Government have recently intimated their desire to contribute to the realization of whatever reforms may be counseled by sentiments of humanity, and by the experience of past or present administration in the Kongo State. As the honorable member is no doubt aware, such an announcement is more cordially welcomed by His Majesty's Government. But, pending the decision to which Blegium may soon come, it is unnecessary to make any further statement at the moment."</p>

</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>

<gap reason="sampling"/>





<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d005">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">The Secretary of State to Minister Wilson.</head>

<head type="sub">[Telegram.]</head>

<head type="sub">Department of State, Washington, January 15, 1907.</head>

<p>Our attitude toward Kongo question reflects deep interest of all classes of American people in the amelioration of conditions. The President's interest in watching the trend toward reform is coupled with earnest desire to see full performance of the obligations of articles 2 and 5 of slave-trade act, to which we are a party. We will cheerfully accord all moral support toward these ends, especially as to all that affects involuntary servitude of the natives. It is the President's desire to contribute by such action toward the realization of whatever reforms may be counseled by the sentiments of humanity and by the experience developed by the past and present workings of the Kongo administration. The Belgian Parliament having adopted principle of annexation and appointed a committee to arrange details, it is alike proper that the wish of the President for substantial improvement of conditions in the Kongo be made known, and that he should for the present observe an expectant attitude, as we understand is the policy of some of the pwoers signatories to the act of Berlin.</p>

<p>Root.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>




<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d006">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">Minister Wilson to the Secretary of State.</head>

<head type="sub">American Legation, Brussels, January 23, 1907.</head>

<p>Sir: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of department's cablegram of January 15.</p>

<p>A study of the cablegram, after its translation, convinced me that
the department had not overlooked the fact that I hold no credentials
to the Kongo Free State and could not for that reason maintain an
official correspondence with it, but, desiring to have our attitude and
the President s views brought to the attention of the Kongo Government,
relied upon me to accomplish that result in such way and manner,
officially or unofficially, as might seem most advisable.</p>

<p>On the day following the receipt of the cablegram I happened to
meet at breakfast, in the house of a mutual friend, Mr. Edmond Carton
de Wiart, the King's secretary, whom I have known more or less intimately
since my first arrival here, and with whom I have frequently 
discussed phases of the Kongo question.</p>

<p>When an opportunity offered, I asked Mr. Carton de Wiart whether
it would suit him, and would be agreeable to His Majesty the King,
to take knowledge of the contents of a cablegram from the Secretary
of State expressing our attitude on the Kongo question. He answered
that he would be very pleased to bring anything of that kind to the
attention of His Majesty in a purely informal way. I accordingly
handed him a copy of the cablegram.</p>

<p>He read the text carefully and understandingly, but did not ask for
a copy. The only comment he made was to inquire whether my government
was fully informed as to the present status of the Kongo
question and the reforms that were in contemplation.</p>

<p>I answered that the legation had transmitted all available information
to Washington.</p>

<p>On the next day, not being entirely sure that I had taken the most
effectual method of bringing our attitude to the knowledge of the
King's Government, I paid a visit to the Chevalier van der Elst, the
secretary-general of the Belgian cabinet, who has been the unofficial
intermediary through which I have acted always in Kongo matters,
and said to him that I was in possession of an expression of the attitude
of our Government relative to the present status of the Kongo 
question, and being without credentials to the Kongo Government I
was uncertain as to what would be the most acceptable manner of
making these views known.</p>

<p>The Chevalier expressed his willingness to convey the contents of
my cablegram to the knowledge of His Majesty, and asked to be permitted
to take a copy of the same. This I gave him, and I understood
him to intimate that I might perhaps receive an acknowledgment,
with some comments, later on.</p>

<p>Yesterday the King's secretary, Mr. Carton de Wiart, came to the
legation to ask me whether the department was in possession of the
Bulletin Officiel de l'Etat Independant du Congo, No. 6, twenty-second
year, June, 1906, which contains, on pages 230-231, under the
caption "Impositions directes et personnelles" articles 1 and 2 of the
royal decree relative to direct and personal taxes to be paid by the
natives. This publication has already been forwarded to the department,
but I take the precaution of inclosing another copy herewith.</p>

<p>Whatever further information I obtain will be promptly transmitted
to the department.</p>

<p>I will be gratified to know whether my course in this matter meets
with the approval of the department.</p>

<p>I have, etc.,<lb/>
Henry Lane Wilson.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>



<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d007">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">Minister Wilson to the Secretary of State.</head>

<head type="sub">[Telegram. -- Paraphrase.]</head>

<head type="sub">American Legation, Brussels, February 7, 1907.</head>

<p>Minister for foreign affairs of Belgium called on me yesterday for
the purpose of expressing his views relative to the possible effect of
the Lodge resolution now before the Senate. Having expressed a
desire that his observations should be transmitted by telegram to
Washington, I requested a memorandum on the subject. This he
gave me, and it is as follows:</p>

<q>The Belgian Government having learned that the vote on the Lodge resolution
is represented in the United States as being conducive to the immediate annexation
of the Kongo by Belgium, the minister for foreign affairs, in a private
conversation, has thought It expedient to call the attention of Mr. Wilson
unofficially to the declarations of the Cabinet and of the leaders of the different
political parties during the last discussion in the Chamber of Representatives
on the Kongo question. according to which Belgium affirmed its intention to
decide the question of annexation after a thorough examination of the subject
and in the free exercise of its Independence and autonomy.</q>

<p>Wilson.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>



<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d008">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">The Acting Secretary of State to Minister Wilson.</head>

<head type="sub">Department of State, Washington, February 9, 1907.</head>

<p>Sir: I have to acknowledge the receipt of your dispatch, No. 146,
of the 23d ultimo, acknowledging the receipt of the department's
telegram of the 15th of the same month communicating to you this
Government's attitude in relation to the Kongo question, reporting
your action in making His Majesty's Government aware of its contents,
except so much thereof as refers to the resolution pending in
the Senate, and asking whether the department approves your course.</p>

<p>In view of the fact adverted to on page 2 of your dispatch, that
you hold no credentials to the Kongo Free State and therefore can
not maintain an official correspondence with it, the department is of
the opinion that you have acted wisely in this matter and approves
your course.</p>

<p>You are requested to furnish the department with a list of the
members of the diplomatic corps at Brussels who are accredited to
the sovereign of the Kongo State and to report how they are so
accredited.</p>

<p>I am, etc.,<lb/>
Robert Bacon.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>




<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d009">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">Senate resolution in regard to the Kongo.</head>

<head type="sub">In the Senate of the United States.</head>

<head type="sub">February 15, 1907.</head>

<p>Whereas it is alleged that the native inhabitants of the Basin of
the Congo have been subjected to inhuman treatment of a character
that should claim the attention and excite the compassion of the people
of the United States: Therefore, be it</p>

<p>Resolved That the President is respectfully advised that in case he
shall find that such allegations are established by proof, he will receive
the cordial support of the Senate in any steps, not inconsistent
with treaty or other international obligations1 or with the traditional
American foreign policy which forbids participation by the United
States in the settlement of political questions which are entirely European
in their scope, he may deem it wise to take in cooperation with
or in aid of any of the powers signatories of the treaty of Berlin for
the amelioration of the condition of such inhabitants.</p>

<p>Attest:<lb/>
(Signed) Charles G. Bennett, Secretary.<lb/>
By H. M. Rose, Assistant Secretary.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>





<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d010">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">Minster Wilson to the Secretary of State.</head>

<head type="sub">[Extract.]</head>

<head type="sub">American Legation, Brussels, March 16, 1907.</head>

<p>Sir: Referring to the last paragraph of the department's No. 93, of
February 9 (File No. 1806/102-103), in which a list of the members
of the diplomatic corps of Brussels who are accredited to the sovereign
of the Kongo State is requested, I have the honor to report
that I find upon investigation that none of the members of the resident
corps are so accredited.</p>

<p>Such business as diplomatic representatives are obliged, under instructions
from their Governments, to transact with the Kongo Free
State is usually carried on very much in the same manner as has
been the custom in this legation.</p>

<p>The experience of other legations in transacting diplomatic business
in this irregular and informal way has not been found satisfactory.</p>

<p>It should be remembered, however, that those acute phases of the
Kongo question requiring delicate handling, accurate information,
and intelligent understanding have developed only during. recent
years, and the necessity for adequate diplomatic representation has
therefore only lately become of pressing importance.</p>

<p>I have no information as to the intention of any government to
accredit representatives to the sovereign of the Kongo State.</p>

<p>I am, however, of the opinion that, in our case, the clothing of the
diplomatic representative of Belgium with additional powers to the
sovereign of the Kongo State would contribute considerably toward
more effective diplomatic action.</p>

<p>I have, etc.,<lb/>
Henry Lane Wilson.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>




<text type="report" xml:id="llg.con.054.001.d011">

<body>

<div1 type="document">

<head type="main">The Acting Secretary of State to Minister Wilson.</head>

<head type="sub">Department of State, Washington, April 1, 1907.</head>

<p>SIR: I have to acknowledge the receipt of your dispatch No. 160,
of the 16th ultimo, reporting that none of the powers has accredited
a diplomatic representative to the sovereign of the Kongo Free State,
and suggesting that if the American minister were so accredited
more effective diplomatic action would result.</p>

<p>In view of the action of the other powers, no change in the practice
of the United States in this regard appears to be necessary.</p>

<p>I am, etc.,<lb/>
Robert Bacon.</p>

</div1>

</body>

</text>


</group>

</text>

</TEI>
